Guide to the University of Chicago. Department of Music. Records 1892-2016
University of Chicago Library
University of Chicago. Department of Music. Records
1892-2016
15 linear feet (14 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
The University of Chicago’s Department of Music was founded in 1931. Since its establishment, it has offered graduate degrees in composition, historical musicology, ethnomusicology, analysis, and theory, as well as an undergraduate Bachelor of Arts degree in music. The Department also hosts a Performance Program that involves hundreds of musicians and numerous ensembles. The collection documents the department’s establishment and history, administrative processes, publications, publicity, and music performances organized by or at the University. The events represented in the records date back to the earliest years of the University before the Department’s establishment.
Information on Use
Access
The records are open for research except Series VII. The documents in this series are restricted for 80 years from their creation.
Historical Note
Prior to the establishment of a Music Department in 1931, the University had formed its band, chorus, and orchestra and housed multiple music clubs. Numerous music performances had been organized and staged at the University of Chicago since the earliest years of its existence. These events include performances by the University’s own band and chorus, student-led music clubs, or prominent guest musicians and groups, local and international.
In 1903, Leon Mandel Assembly Hall (Mandel Hall) opened its door to listeners for the first time with a concert by the Chicago Symphony Orchestra and since became one of the most important historic spaces for music performances at the University. Bond Chapel and Rockefeller Memorial Chapel, built in 1926 and 1928 respectively, became other major venues for the University’s music programs. Recitals, chamber concerts, and operas performed in these spaces are well documented in the collection. Of special note is the frequent appearance of the Chicago Symphony Orchestra, which had formerly been named after its founder Theodore Thomas, in Mandel Hall from 1904-1934.
The Department of Music was established in 1931 as part of the Division of Humanities through a special gift from an anonymous donor. Following the department’s establishment, a University symphony orchestra was created during the academic year 1931-1932. The department’s first chair as well as the symphony orchestra director was the music scholar and composer Carl Bricken. In the following years and decades, the Department recruited such leading scholars and composers as Leonard B. Meyer, Edward Lowinsky, Ralph Shapey, and Howard Mayer Brown, and came to prominence in the 1960s as a major center of musical research and composition.
The Department’s Performance Program involves choirs, orchestras, and ensembles, and aims at providing the students with opportunities to participate in a variety of music performances. Since the establishment of the University Symphony Orchestra, several other ensembles were formed within the Department’s Performance Program. They include the Collegium Musicum, Rockefeller Chapel Choir, Motet Choir, Contemporary Chamber Players (later to be named “Contempo”), and New Music Ensemble. The collection contains documents about the musical performances of these ensembles over the decades. Moreover, the Department of Music hosted many other programs featuring visiting musicians and orchestras, as well as lectures and conferences.
The University of Chicago Chamber Music Series, founded in 1943, later grew into “The University of Chicago Presents” concert series with the mission of sharing world-class music through concerts and educational programs with audiences across Chicago and its surrounding suburbs. In the 1960s, the series came under the stewardship of the Department of Music at the University, where it has since resided. The University of Chicago Presents is also represented in the collection.
Scope Note
Series I, Administrative, consists of documents related to the Department’s administrative processes, including departmental reports and correspondence, meeting minutes, the relations with other University units and external parties, such as the Fromm Music Foundation. The folders in this series are arranged chronologically, except when multiple folders formed a thematic group.
Series II, Publications and Publicity, contains the Department’s publications, such as booklets, guides, calendars, and press releases, as well as extensive documentation of the press coverage of music programs. The latter is represented by newspaper clippings. The folders are first grouped thematically and then arranged chronologically. Researchers are also encouraged to consult Series VI for the scrapbooks that contain newspaper clippings about the music programs.
Series III, Events, comprises programs, flyers, posters, and invitation cards for a variety of music performances across decades. The series is divided into two subseries. Subseries 1, Performances and Programs General, brings together materials about miscellaneous performances and programs staged at the University. The folders in this subseries are grouped according to general types of the events or other unifying features. Each folder group is arranged chronologically in itself. Subseries 2, University Ensembles, consists of materials that document performances or performance series by various music ensembles belonging to or affiliated with the University of Chicago. In this subseries, certain folders belonging to the same ensemble are grouped together. The folders and folder groups are arranged chronologically. For more on music events, researchers are encouraged to consult Series VI, Oversize, for the scrapbooks that contain flyers, programs, and posters.
Series IV, Notated Music and Libretti, is arranged chronologically.
Series V, Photographs, consists of photographs of the Department’s faculty and music performances, and is arranged chronologically.
Series VI, Oversize, contains several scrapbooks. The scrapbooks, created over the course of sixty years, bring together newspaper clippings, programs, flyers, and posters of music events. They are arranged chronologically.
Series VII, Restricted, consists of documents that contain evaluative student materials. These documents are restricted for 80 years from the date of creation.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
University of Chicago. Office of the President. Hutchins Administration. Records
University of Chicago. Office of the President. Levi Administration. Records
University of Chicago. Band. Records
University of Chicago. Department of Music. Choral Ensembles. Records
Music Relating to the University of Chicago. Records
Shapey, Ralph. Papers
Lowinsky, Edward E. Papers
Meyer, Leonard B. Papers
Subject Headings
Theodore Thomas Orchestra (Chicago, Ill.); Levarie, Siegmund, 1914-2010; Fromm, Paul, 1906-1987; University of Chicago. Department of Music; University of Chicago. Symphony Orchestra; Contemporary Chamber Players of the University of Chicago; Rockefeller Chapel Choir (University of Chicago); University of Chicago. Department of Music. Motet Choir; Chicago Symphony Orchestra; Fromm Music Foundation
INVENTORY
- Series I: Administrative
  - Department of Music - History and Departmental Correspondence, 1931-1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The University of Chicago Band, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The University of Chicago Opera Association - Establishment, Finances, Correspondence, 1934-1936 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Student grades, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Department of Music - Meeting Minutes, 1944-1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Humanities Visiting Committee - Members Lists and Correspondence, 1952-1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Fromm Music Foundation - Programs, Finances, Correspondence, 1952-1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fromm Music Foundation - Paul Fromm’s Correspondence, 1967-1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Graduate Fellowship Announcements, 1964-1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Graduate Degree Requirements, 1965-1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series II: Publications and Publicity
  - Department of Music Press Coverage - Newspaper Clippings, 1929-1940 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Department of Music Press Coverage - Newspaper Clippings, 1941-1947 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Department of Music Press Coverage - Newspaper Clippings, 1961-1967 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Press Releases, 1940-1964 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Flyers and Posters for Tryouts, Auditions, Performance Opportunities, 1949-2011 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Societas Campanariorum - Press Release and Calendar for the 50th Anniversary, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - “A Center for Music at the University of Chicago” - Booklet, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Season and Event Calendars, 1981-2016 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - “Chicago Scene” - Newsletter, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - “Goodspeed Notes” - Newsletter of the Department of Music, 205 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - “Pacifica Quartet” - Newsletter, 2005-2006 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - “Graduate Study in Music” - Guide, no date (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - “Graduate Study in Music” - Guide, no date (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - “Music at the University of Chicago” - Booklet by the Department of Music, no date (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Series III: Events
  - Subseries 1: Performances and Programs General
    - Recitals - Programs, 1900-1920 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Recitals - Programs, 1921-1940 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Recitals - Programs, Posters, Flyers, 1945-2013 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Music Performances - Programs, 1892-1918 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Music Performances - Programs, 1922-1939 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Music Performances - Programs, Posters, 1941-1955 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Music Performances - Programs, Flyers, Invitation Cards, 1960-1976 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Music Performances - Programs, Posters, Invitation Cards, 1981-2000 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Music Performances - Programs, Posters, Invitation Cards, no date (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Chicago Symphony Orchestra - Concert Programs, 1904-1920 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Chicago Symphony Orchestra - Concert Programs, 1921-1934 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Chicago Symphony Orchestra - Concert Programs, 1965-1969 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Brahms Festival - Flyer, Program, Newspaper Clippings, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Composers Concert - Programs and Invitations, 1943-1946 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - University Concerts - Concert Series Programs, 1945-1951 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - University Concerts - Concert Series Programs, 1951-1957 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Lectures and Conferences - Programs and Invitation Cards, 1945-2000 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 2: University Ensembles
    - Musical Clubs - Concert Programs, 1895-1900, Women’s Glee Club Women’s Mandolin Club Glee Club Mandolin Club Banjo Club Serenade Club (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Musical Clubs - Concert Programs, 1901-1920, Glee Club Mandolin Club Banjo Quintette The Women’s Glee Club The Men’s Glee Club (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Musical Clubs - Concert Programs, 1922-1955, Glee Club Intercollegiate Glee Clubs (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - University of Chicago Orchestra - Concert Programs, 1913-1917 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - University Symphony Orchestra - Concert Programs, 1932-1940 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - University Symphony Orchestra - Concert Programs, 1941-1950 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - University Symphony Orchestra - Concert Programs, 1951-1960 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - University Symphony Orchestra - Concert Programs, 1966-1979 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - University Symphony Orchestra - Concert Programs, 1993-2013 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - University Chorus and Orchesis - Music Performances, 1933-1935 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Collegium Musicum - Programs, Posters, Flyers, Press Coverage, 1939-1967 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Contemporary Chamber Players of the University of Chicago - Concert Programs and Posters, 1964-2015 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - New Music Ensemble - Concert Posters, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Series IV: Notated Music and Libretti
  - “Choral Music, including piano and vocal parts, 1935-1936 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - “Shvanda, the Piper” by Jaromir Weinberger - Complete Opera Libretto, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - “A Service of Advent Lessons and Carols” - Musical Scores, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - “Noah’s Flood” by Benjamin Britten - Complete Opera Libretto, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Centennial Songbook of the University of Chicago – Music for 22 Songs, 1991-1992 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - “The Life of the Virgin Mary” by Paul Hindemith - Complete Song Cycle, no date (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Football Songs and Cheers, no date (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Series V: Photographs
  - Photographs from opera performance “Pimpinone,” 1939 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Photographs from opera performance “Music Master,” 1947 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Photographs of Siegmund Levarie and Music Department Faculty, no date (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Series VI: Oversize
  - Two scrapbooks - Event programs, flyers, posters, newspaper clippings, 1933-1939 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook - Event programs, flyers, posters, newspaper clippings, 1943-1946 (Box 7)
  - Scrapbook - Newspaper clippings, 1947-1951 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook titled “Musical Events 1964-1965” - Flyers, programs, posters, newspaper clippings, 1964-1965 (Box 9)
  - Scrapbook - Flyers, programs, posters, newspaper clippings, 1967-1993 (Box 10)
  - Scrapbook - Flyers, programs, posters, 1971-1987 (Box 11)
  - Scrapbook - Flyers, programs, posters, 1987-1995 (Box 12)
- Series VII: Restricted
  The documents in this series are restricted for 80 years from date of creation.
  - Fellowship application documents - Paula Kelch Elliott, 1965 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Fellowship application documents - Thomas Charles Elliott, 1965 (Box 13, Folder 2)